<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>M. Antonius de Dominis Archbishop of Spalato, declares the cause of his returne, out of England. Translated out of the Latin copy, printed at Rome this prese[n]t yeare</title>
            <title>Marcus Antonius de Dominis archiepisc. Spalaten. sui reditus ex Anglia consilium exponit. English</title>
            <author>De Dominis, Marco Antonio, 1560-1624.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1623</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 103 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 53 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A20601</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 7000</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120942</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99856133</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99856133</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21656</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A20601)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21656)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1200:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>M. Antonius de Dominis Archbishop of Spalato, declares the cause of his returne, out of England. Translated out of the Latin copy, printed at Rome this prese[n]t yeare</title>
                  <title>Marcus Antonius de Dominis archiepisc. Spalaten. sui reditus ex Anglia consilium exponit. English</title>
                  <author>De Dominis, Marco Antonio, 1560-1624.</author>
                  <author>Coffin, Edward, 1571-1626.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>86 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by the English College Press] Permissu superiorum,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Saint-Omer :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.DC.XXIII. [1623]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation, by Edward Coffin, of: Marcus Antonius de Dominis archiepisc. Spalaten. sui reditus ex Anglia consilium exponit.</note>
                  <note>Identification of printer from STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: M. Antonius de Dominis his recantation.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Emmanuel College (University of Cambridge). Library.</note>
                  <note>Tightly bound; pages 4-5, 34-45, 54-55 from Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery copy filmed at end.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Apologetic works --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Catholic converts --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21656:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21656:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>M. ANTONIVS DE DOMINIS ARCHBISHOP OF SPALATO, Declares the cauſe of his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne, out of England.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tranſlated out of the Latin Copy, printed at Rome this preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t yeare.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vnus Dominus, Vna Fides, Vnum Baptiſma.</hi>
               </p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>One Lord, One Fayth, One Baptiſme.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Permiſſu Superiorum,</hi> M.DC.XXIII.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21656:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:21656:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:21656:3"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:21656:3"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HIS may ſeeme a ſmall worke (good Reader) for ſo great a ſca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dall as hath beene giuen by the Authour, but it is an abridgement only of another more large, &amp; ample, that is to enſue; and yet in this, thou mayst perceiue how men may ſo farre be tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported by vnbridled paſſions, as to fall into open ſchiſme, &amp; hereſy: on the other ſide thou mayſt ſee alſo, the force and efficacy of Gods grace in recalling of ſinners by true repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tance to his loue, and fauour. Let the one of theſe ballance the other, and let the latter cancell the fault of his committed errour. <note place="margin">1 Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſilium Profectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis. 2. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſilium Reditus.</note> That was wicked, pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and detestable; this is vertuous, exemplar, and laudable. The latter counſayle is alwayes wont to be more ponderous, graue, and iudici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous then the former; eſpecially when as the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>former is recalled by the latter.</p>
            <p>His reuolt you will ſay was ſcandalous. True. But now —</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vna eade<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> manus vulnꝰ ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> tulit.</hi> He hath in part made ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds for his former fault by his ſubmiſſiue confeſsion: and this <hi>learned Prelate</hi> (as an vnlearned Myniſter stiled him) <note place="margin">Hall in his honour of the mary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed clergy. pag. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>5.</note> 
               <hi>that had honoured the Engliſh Church with a Dalmatian Pall, that had paſſed ouer the Alpes to leaue Rome, that was ſo potent a Proteſtant as none of al our
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:21656:4"/> Bandogges durſt faſten vpon him,</hi> hath now withdrawn both Pall &amp; Honour from that Church, hath left <hi>Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d,</hi> is returned ouer the Alpes to <hi>Rome</hi> againe, &amp; like a bandog indeed hath fastened himſelfe on the English wolues, &amp; bites ſo hard as he makes them bleed; &amp; fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther makes all Protestants to ſee their weaknes (if yet they haue eyes to ſee) &amp; <note place="margin">Hall ibid. in the anſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to the aduertiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> that the whole <hi>Region of Deuines and thoſe ſo incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable, that may ſet Rome to ſchoole,</hi> could not defend themſelues from open Schiſme and Hereſy; nor perſwade one man, &amp; he ſuch a one as offered himſelfe freely into their hands, to remaine &amp; continue amongst them. <hi>Magna eſt veritas, &amp; praeualet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thou mayſt further ſee, with what care and ſincerity our Aduerſaries write agaynſt vs, how they examine the matters they handle, how little truth &amp; learning, &amp; how much, lies, detractio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, forgeries, &amp; paſsionate fancies are regarded. By theſe baſe means, &amp; shameful shifts muſt hereſy be mantained, Catholiks impugned, &amp; iniured, all vertue depreſſed, &amp; troden vnder foote. Let the example of one be a warning vnto all, &amp; let the Retreate of this ſeduced Bishop make men looke on what ground they ſtand, &amp; not hazard their ſaluation, bought with the ranſome of our Sauiours bloud, vpon the falſe, Heretical, and Schiſmaticall opinions of theſe times.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:21656:4"/>
            <head>The Cauſe of <hi>M. Antonius de Dominis</hi> his Returne out of England.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>XCELLENTLY (as all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thinges) doth the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt by the mouth of Saint Paul reckon amongſt the works of the fleſh, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions, emulations, angers, debates diſſentions, and ſects: theſe vnfortunate fruits of this wicked tree I hauing ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, or rather out of the corrupt diſeaſe of my minde greedily deuoured, haue now thought requiſite, after the hole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome receite of Gods grace, to caſt vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne, and make a perfect euacuation of this contracted filth. This that I might the more ſafely and readily doe, and my ſelfe openly reprehend, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne the manifold errours that haue
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:21656:5"/> enſued of the wicked reſolution of my former bad departure; I reſolued with my ſelfe the beſt courſe to be, leauing the ſchoole of errours, falſities, and he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies, to returne of myne owne accord to the holy Roman Church, the one &amp; only pillar, and ſingular foundation of truth, and mother of all Catholikes, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which ſo wickedly I had departed; &amp; therefore firſt of all I will explicate this reprehenſion, condemning, and dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation of my errours paſt: after that I will recount other cauſes for which I was to leaue England, and other here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall countreyes, and to returne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne to the holy Catholike Roman Church.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It is a moſt ancient diſeaſe of our corrupt nature, as it were by inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance conueighed from our firſt parent vnto all his poſterity, that when we erre and doe agaynſt that which is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded, we eyther coyne friuolous excuſes: <note place="margin">Geneſ. 3.</note> 
               <hi>The woman whome thou hast giuen me &amp;c.</hi> or elſe defend our faultes, and with the counterfeit garment of iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and vertue, labour all we can to maske and couer them. This to haue
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:21656:5"/> befallen vnto me I doe both confeſſe, &amp; lament. The diſeaſe of my ſoule where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with I was ſicke before my departure was, in that I truſted to much to my own prudence agaynſt that wholeſome counſayle of the Wiſe-man, <note place="margin">Prouerb. 3.</note> 
               <hi>ne innitaris prudentiae tuae,</hi> and out of the confidence of my ſmall wit, being of ſo ſmall reach I iudged too raſhly of matters of Fayth: beſides this a certaine frenzy of rage, not that which ſome ignorant companions only wiſe in their owne conceit, obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted vnto me when I was to returne out of England, for that, forſooth, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne Promotions, which in vayne I thirſted after were denyed me, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>togeather cauſed of my vnreaſonable im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patience whiles I tooke it moſt grieuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſly to be vnder them, of whome in the Booke of the cauſes of my departure I haue without all cauſe complayned: theſe things carryed me vpon the ſhelfs and ſands, theſe did beate my barke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt the rocks, theſe ſharpened my wit to peſtiferous thoughts, theſe were the cauſe why I fondly feigned errours of the Roman Church, wherby I might excuſe my departure; theſe finally caſt
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:21656:6"/> me on thoſe extreme coaſtes, vvhere I went, and that I might ſeeme to haue done well, and in ſome ſort endeauour to auoyd the imputation of imprudency and raſhnes, and of hereſy alſo, firſt for defence of my departure I ſet forth my purpoſe and intention in the ſame, then other volumes, and bookes fraught with ſuch things as eyther the art of fei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gning, or forging ſuggeſted, or the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the fleſh did prompt vnto me: and vvhiles the ſicknes boyled in my breſt within, and the ſtings of wrath did pricke my exulcerated mynd, the itch of my tongue, and pen did breake forth into an impoſtume. Many things which heretikes, enemyes of the Sea Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like did belieue, affirme, and profeſſe, ſeemed to me, now blinded by my ſelfe to be credible, ſome to be true; when as yet I had neuer brought theſe contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſies to the touchſtone of true diuini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, nor had throughly diſcuſſed them, for I had not ended any part of the Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall Commonwealth in which I had determined to treat of points of religion, and rules of fayth; nor yet had I ſo much as begunne it, howſoeuer in
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:21656:6"/> the booke of the cauſe of my departure I ſayd, that I had already finiſhed all theſe books. Hence it came that I raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly relying on the ſlaunders of heretikes and not on the Catholike fayth, entitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led one of my books, <hi>Of the cauſe of my departure,</hi> and another in Italian, <hi>The rockes of Chriſtian shipwracke,</hi> and another <hi>A certayne ſermon,</hi> which I filled ful of er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, and hereſies for the moſt part, in hatred of the holy Roman Church, and Sea Apoſtolike, and of thoſe Popes by whom I thought my ſelfe to haue byn iniured; and affirmed thoſe and many other things vvhich before I knew to be falſe, and hereticall, and after at leaſt in part, my ſelfe miſliked, and did whils I wrote in England from my hart deteſt them, becauſe they conteyne open he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſyes, agaynſt the Catholike truth, and are contrary to ſound doctrine; I meane to that which the Catholicke Roman Church hath alwayes held, and holds at this day: agaynſt which whatſoeuer, or wherſoeuer is written or ſayd by me, that in al and euery part I do condemne and deteſt; and I will better, &amp; more at large by Gods help, condemne and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:21656:7"/> deteſt the ſame, in the confutation of my bookes of the Eccleſiaſticall Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, &amp; other bookes that I haue written agaynſt the truth: for I ſubmit my ſelfe, and all my bookes to the moſt holy iudgement, and cenſure of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Roman and Apoſtolicall Sea, the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe and guide of all other Churches.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In the meane tyme here in this exchange for a new, and ſounder reſolution, I moſt deteſt the former of my departure, the Infamous Rockes of the ſhipwrackes, of my ſelfe eſpecially, and heretikes, but not of Catholikes, &amp; moreouer the Sermon mentioned; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall I ſhame by caſting of the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which I had made for myſelfe, to ſhew my nakednes, becauſe I was not aſhamed agaynſt all law and conſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cience to breake forth into vayne fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, open ſlaunders, and filthy he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies. <note place="margin">Dioſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rides l. 6. c. 44.</note> The ſting, and poyſon of the ſcorpion by bruzing of the ſame ſcorpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that ſtong, hath a preſent remedy. If the voluntary breaking, and bruzing of my ſelfe bring remedy to this poyſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned wound (in caſe any ſo wounded haue repented him himſelfe) I ſhall
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:21656:7"/> eſteeme this my bruzing, deiection, and mortification for happy: let the glory of the Catholike Church and Sea Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like ſtand immoueable, yea euen with the greateſt loſſe of temporal goods that can befall me; and ſince that ſo wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedly I haue gone about to weaken, and infring it, this courſe cannot (at leaſt before God) but be glorious vnto me.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Firſt therfore I confeſſe, &amp; in conſcience truly, &amp; ſincerly teſtify that I wrote that booke of the <hi>Cauſe of my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture,</hi> and the other two, to wit the <hi>Rocks,</hi> and <hi>Sermon,</hi> not out of ſincerity of hart, not good co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience, not out of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feygned faith, but that I might caſt ſome colourable excuſe on my ſhamefull de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partur, &amp; that I might be the more grat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and welcome vnto the heretickes, to whom like a wretch I went, or with whome I did conuerſe. The ten yeares labour which I bragged of in the book of my departure, was not imployed in maturity of deliberation, grauity of iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement, diſcuſſion of truth, but all that vvhile I ſtudyed hovv to finiſh that vaine, fruitles, and pernicious worke
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:21656:8"/> 
               <hi>of the Eccleſiaſticall commonwealth,</hi> &amp; coyne bold, and hereticall fictions, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſatisfy the impotent force of myne owne rage; in ſo much as that vocation was not deuine, but diabolicall, not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired by the holy Ghoſt, but ſuggeſted by a bad ſpirit, vexing me worſe then it did Saul with the ſpirit of giddines: <note place="margin">2. Reg. 18 v. 10.</note> but for my returne I doubt not but that it is to be aſcribed vnto Gods true voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, his diuine ſpirit calling me backe to my Mother, the holy Catholique Church.</p>
            <p n="5">5. I ſayd, that the behauiour of the court of Rome was the cauſe why I ſhould for euer abhorre it: I am not ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, that herein I ſpake ill, for there were not wanting then, nor yet are at Rome very many co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſpicuous examples of piety, &amp; all Chriſtian vertues which are able to delight, and allure religious, or well diſpoſed mynds. I ſayd that out of the forbidding of hereticall books to be read, do ſpring euill ſuſpitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s which get credit to the books of heretiks, and induce men to belieue ſomewhat to be in them vvhich Catholikes could not confute, and this I acknowledge to haue
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:21656:8"/> been ſpoken by me, not without great iniury to the Catholike ſaith, who haue found in their bookes, I meane of here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes, falſe, hereticall, ſcandalous, and peſtiferous doctrine, from reading of which, leaſt the Faythfull be infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted they are worthily to be reſtray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: for not vnto priuate men who read thoſe bookes, but vnto the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtours, the iudgement of fayth hath euer and doth ſtill appertayne, that they may know which are poiſoned paſturs, and remoue their flockes far from them. Moreouer the arguments of heretiks are deceytfull, ſophiſticall, and haue moſt eaſy ſolutions. I affirmed the doctrine of thoſe who oppoſe themſelues to the Church of Rome, nothing at all, or ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry little to degenerate from the pure do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the primitiue Church, and this alſo is falſe: for the opinions in which they differ from Catholiks, are all of them moſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to thoſe which that Church held, &amp; nothing can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince them more certainly of errour the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the authority of the ancient Church fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which they by theſe noueltyes haue very far departed: in ſo much as for this
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:21656:9"/> cauſe they are condemned as heretikes by the Church of Rome: it is therefore to be deteſted, &amp; I doe deteſt that which I ſayd, Therefore the religion of Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants to be condemned of the Church, becauſe it is contrary to the ſenſe, and corrupted manners of the Court of Rome. I ſaid, that in Rome by extreme violence were coyned new articles of beliefe, and this truly I did ſay both a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt my knowledge and conſcience, for I neuer ſaw any ſuch matter, nor any man elſe, as moſt certainly I know, for none can ſay that there are new articles coyned, when there are only added the true declaratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s &amp; explicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the true articles, &amp; thoſe gathered out of the holy ſcripturs, traditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the Fathers, &amp; very rules of religion. Againe I endeuored to depriue the Roman Church of the titles of Catholike, and Vniuerſall, wherin I exceedingly erred: for by the Roman Church is not vnderſtood that ſpeciall, and particuler Church alone, which is at Rome, but the collection of all other Churches adhering to the Roman in v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of the ſame fayth, and ſubiection to the ſame chiefe Biſhop, whereſoeuer
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:21656:9"/> they be, albeit in the vttermoſt coaſtes and corners of the earth. And doubtles this is moſt true, &amp; of me, both by word of mouth, as England it ſelfe can teſtify, and in my written treatiſes of the <hi>Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall commonwealth,</hi> and in that part which laſt of all (I heare) is printed in Germany, I haue euinced, that there is no other Catholike Church but the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, vnderſtanding thereby that parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular with the other adhering thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to; wheras all other companies of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians are defiled with hereſies, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by ſchiſme deuided and ſeparated from the truth, are out of the Catholike, vniuerſall, and true Church of Chriſt; and theſe blind ſoules with their blynd guides, ruſh and fall headlong into the pit of hell, which I in my errour moſt wickedly and without grieuous iniury affirmed of the Roman Catholikes: for from the Roman Church at all times to all other Churchs the moſt ſhining light of the pure and incorrupted fayth hath flowed, and at this preſent flowes. I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member alſo, that in the preface of my bookes of the <hi>Eccleſiasticall commonwealth,</hi> I vſed certayne wordes, by which I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuated
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:21656:10"/> all ſuch to be in the Catholike Church, who had receaued baptiſme in the name of the Trinity; but albeit the words haue an ill ſound, &amp; make all he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticall Churches true &amp; ſound me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers of the true Catholike Church, which is moſt falſe, and hereticall, yet my mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning was, that the Arian, Neſtorian, Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichian, all hereticall and condemned Churches in tymes paſt, ſhould be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, and only the true belieuers to be retayned: which true belieuers I thought then to be many more then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed they are, and many Churches tain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with theſe latter Hereſyes, and by Schiſme deuided, I erroneouſly iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to pertaine to the Catholike; but though the Catholike Church be ſo denominated for her Vniuerſality, yet this Vniuerſality includes no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then the true orthodoxe, or right belieuing Churches, ſpread ouer the whole world, which remayne in vnity with the Roman. And truly the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſality of the Roman Church doth conſiſt not only in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinual durance neuer yet interrupted, or euer after to be, and conſtance of ſound beliefe, but alſo
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:21656:10"/> is vniuerſall, becauſe the ſelfe ſame fayth of Rome, and ſupreme gouernement are extended after the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming of Chriſt to all places, and all Nations: for which reſpect euen in theſe latter ages, it is no leſſe to be tearmed Catholike, then it was in the tyme of the ancient Fathers, becauſe the fayth of the Roman Church euen at this tyme, is propagated in the moſt remote, &amp; vaſt regions of the Eaſt and Weſt Indyes, euen vnto the furtheſt corners of the earth; in ſo much as the children of this Church euen in theſe dayes paſſing by continuall trauel from the riſing of the Sunne vnto the ſetting, and carrying with them the Fayth of Chriſt, &amp; offering cleane ſacrifices, that now may be ſayd eſpecially to be fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, which God pronounced by the mouth of Malachy: <note place="margin">Malach. 1. v. 11.</note> 
               <hi>Ab ortu ſolis vſque ad occaſum magnum est nomen meum in gentibus, &amp; in omni loco ſacrificatur, &amp; offertur nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimeo oblatio munda.</hi> From the riſing of the ſunne vnto the ſetting my name is great amongſt the Gentills, &amp; in euery place there is ſacrificed and offered vnto my name a pure oblation. Neither was it a leſſe iniury, and ſlaunder, when I
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:21656:11"/> ſaid that I had noted very many nouel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes, and errors of the Court of Rome; which nouelties, which errors, I ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther now, or euer yet noted, and I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge it to be moſt falſe, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe it for ſuch, that euer there were, or are in Rome ſuch errors, out of which the ruine, and ſlaughter of ſoules doth proceed, the peace of the Church is troubled, or publick ſcandalls haue, or doe ariſe; truly next after God all peace of the Catholike Church, her totall tranquillity, and the euerlaſting ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of ſoules is to be aſcribed to the care, and ſollicitude of the Roman Church. I ſayd, that the more potent Biſhops vnder the Biſhop of Rome were but equiuocall, or counterfeit Biſhops: and this ſaying co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teins no leſſe falſhood then iniury in it, and therefore as ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latiue I condemne it; for they are true, and lawfull Biſhops, made by lawfull ordination. I affirmed others who were not Potentates, and Princes to haue loſt the proper dignity and power of Biſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ops: and truly this is alſo a ſlaunder, for hierarchical ſubordinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the Church hath been alwaies neceſſary: much more
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:21656:11"/> doe I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demne as an hereſy that which I ſaid, the Church no longer to remayn vnder the Biſhop of Rome; for as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſpecifyed, and earneſtly auouched only the Church of Rome with the reſt adhering therunto, is the true Church of Chriſt, &amp; that others are no Churchs at all. And to conclude much in few, I perceyue that in the firſt booke of my departure, I ſpecially endeauoured to infringe the primacy of the B. of Rome, in which poynt I deny not, but that I ſpake againſt the fayth of the whole Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Church, and therefore greatly to haue erred, for both by the Euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall ordinance, traditions of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, definitions of the holy Synods, &amp; Generall Councells, by very many de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees of Popes, and common teſtimony of Fathers, and eccleſiaſticall hiſtories, it is manifeſt, and cleere the B. of Rome alwayes to haue been taken for head of the whole Church, to haue beene ſo ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by Chriſt our Lord, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes to haue been taken for a ſingular oracle, to whome no leſſe the Eaſt then the Weſt, in all doubts of fayth ſhould ſue for inſtruction of beliefe, definition,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:21656:12"/> &amp; ſecure doctrine, as a maiſter appointed vs by God, who ſhould by his office teach and direct his Church, any ſchol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler may obſerue very many examples in which the Biſhops of Rome direct the Patriarkes, and Biſhops of the Eaſt, they warne them, rebuke them, teach them, condemne them, abſolue them, depoſe them, reſtore them, controle them, and that euen out of their office, and power ouer them; and the others checked by the Popes, humbly gaue them eare, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed, reſiſted not, or reclaymed; and briefely, it is cleare by the confeſſion of all the Catholike Church, the whole ſpirit of Chriſt, for determining of theſe things which belong vnto fayth, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide in the ſole, and one viſible ſupreme head of the ſame Church, which is on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Pope, the chiefe Biſhop, and <hi>S. Peters</hi> ſuccceſſor.</p>
            <p n="5">5. I freely confeſſe that the booke which I called <hi>the Rockes of Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrack</hi> did exceedingly diſpleaſe me pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently after that it was ſet forth, for without all choyce had of the matter, without all diſcuſſion or ſearch of truth I hudled it vp, that I might ſome way
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:21656:12"/> or other pleaſe the Engliſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, after my arriuall amongſt them; in writing of which I conſidered, and layd open not what was true, but what pleaſed beſt the enemies of the Church, eſpecially the vulgar, and vnlearned multitude: and this booke whiles I was in England, &amp; preparing for my departure being obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted vnto me by the King, and other men, I did in plain wordes deteſt it, and my ſelfe withſtood the greater part of hereſyes which it conteynes, and as far as I was able impugned them: al which here agayne I reiect, abhorre, and deteſt. The hereſies were theſe. The B. of Rome not to be Chriſts vicar on earth, and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible head of his Church; that he had no power ouer temporall things; implicite fayth to auayle nothing but much to hurt the faithfull; the excommunicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the law to be vain buggs; the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements of the Church not to bind vnder mortall ſinne; the vnity of the Church not to be taken from one viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble head; the Pope to be the capitall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enemy of the whole Church; the Maſſe to be no true ſacrifice; the ceremonies of the Maſſe to be light Comical geſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:21656:13"/> no transſubſtantiation to be made; auricular confeſſion with abſolution to be no true Sacrament; that there is no purgatory; ſatisfaction for releaſe of the puniſhment after that the fault is forgiuen not to be neceſſary; no In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgences to be, but of ſuch penaltyes only as are impoſed; the Saintes not to be inuocated; the worſhip of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes, and Images not to be lawfull; that there is no merit of good wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes to euerlaſting life. Theſe, and the the like errours, and manifeſt hereſies not ſo much myne, and new, as of the auncient, and modern heretickes, and their bablings, and doating dreames, condemned alwayes by the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Church in many holy generall Councells, are miſerable rockes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which ſuch as approach make la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable ſhipwracke of their faith and euerlaſtinge ſaluation; and therefore I fly from them as far as I am able: and leaſt that I ſhould haue beene caſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way vppon them in England, I was of neceſſity to depart from thence, and rerurne to the true Church, the port and harbour of Catholickes, and forſake,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:21656:13"/> deteſt, anathematize or accurſe all the foreſayd errors, and whatſoeuer o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers if there be any other in thoſe bookes, which agree not with the faith expreſſed in the ſacred Councells, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially in the late Councell of Trent: on the other ſide I imbrace, and auer the contrary truthes, to wit, the chiefe Biſhop of Rome by Chriſts iuſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to be his Vicar on earth; to be the viſible head of the militant Church which alwayes hath beene viſible, with full power receaued from God to gouerne and order the ſame; the ſame Biſhopp of Rome to haue po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer ouer temporall thinges <hi>in ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne ad ſpiritualia;</hi> the implicite fayth to be profitable, and ſometymes neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, as when one without his fault hath no expreſſe faith, or beliefe of ſome articles; the excommunications of the law, or deliuered <hi>ipſo facto,</hi> to be of force, and to be feared, as induced by exceeding great reaſon, and lawfull power; the Popes to be able to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate all faithfull people of what place, or countrey ſoeuer, in caſe they deſerue to be ſo cenſured,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:21656:14"/> the commaundements of the Church bynd all vnder mortall ſinne to obſerue them; the vnity of the Church chiefly to depend vpon the one, viſible head thereof; the B. of Rome to be the true, lawfull, &amp; towards the ſheepe of Chriſt as it behoueth, the profitable Paſtor of the whole Church, the only eternall ſaluation of which I deſire he may al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes thirſt, and ſeeke with all care; in in the Maſſe to be offered vp vnto God a true, proper, and propitiatory ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, the ceremonies of the Maſſe ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the Fathers, and Paſtors of the Church by the inſpiration of the holy Ghoſt, to be holy, myſtical, profitable, and by all meanes to be retayned; tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation to be made in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Aultar, that is the conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of turning of the whole ſubſtance of bread into the body, &amp; of the whole ſubſtance of wine into the bloud of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt; by Sacramentall ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution wherby the prieſt abſolues the penitent, to be exerciſed a true and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per power of binding, and loſing ſins, which our Lord gaue to the miniſters of his Sacraments in the Church, to be
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:21656:14"/> purgatory in that manner, as the holy Roman, &amp; Apoſtolicke Church teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it to be graunted; ſatisfaction to be much avayleable for the releaſement of the puniſhment after that the ſinne is forgiuen; the vſe of pardons in the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Church to whome Chriſt hath giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> power to beſtow them, to be moſt ancient, moſt ſoueraygne, and appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by the authority of holy Councels; the Saints not only without all errour of the faithfull to be inuocated, but fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that it is good, &amp; profitable to haue recourſe to their prayers, and help; the worſhip of Reliques, and images to be good, lawfull, and profitable; which cannot be abrogated without the ſpot of hereſy; the merit of eternall life to depend of our good workes. The later General Councels which are of ſuprea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me authority in the Church, my ſtomak being ouer charged with ill humours, I did often deſpiſe, eſpecially the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cells of Florence, &amp; Trent, many times alſo that of Conſtance, and through my procuring a certayn hiſtory came forth in print of the Councell of Trent, of the truth of which hiſtory I had no
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:21656:15"/> certainty, yea it is worthily ſuſpected of impoſture: in theſe thinges alſo I confeſſe that I erred very much, for I affirme all the moſt wholſome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees of theſe Councells with full fayth to be imbraced by all the Catholikes.</p>
            <p n="6">6. In a certayn ſermon of mine had in Italian at London the firſt ſonday in Aduent, and printed, I ſet down theſe errours, which being after repeated a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne in the booke of the Rocks, now I haue worthily deteſted. In that ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon I framed a certayn night of papall errours in the Roman Church, wheras indeed in the Roman Church alone and others conioyned therewith there is true light, the true, and only moſt ſhining day, out of which (in England eſpecially) is continuall, &amp; moſt darke night. In the Church of Rome, the light of truth, the true, and ſincere vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of the holy ſcriptures driues far away from it al the darkenes of errours, with which darknes miſerable Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d being ouercaſt, groapeth like a blind man at noone day. I ſayd in the ſame ſermon, and reiterated agayne in the booke of the Rocks, that <hi>S. Peter</hi> was
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:21656:15"/> neuer at Rome, but this as a ſoule, and ignorant lye I freely confeſſe is to be condemned. I made all the Apoſtles in planting, and gouerning the Church to be equall, whereas notwithſtanding the ſupremacy of <hi>S. Peter</hi> ouer them is cleare by the very goſpells and Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall traditions. I affirmed the Biſhops to ſucceed the Apoſtles with equall power, and to be Biſhops <hi>in ſolidum</hi> of the Vniuerſall Church, whereas yet Biſhops are but Paſtors of particuler Churchs, &amp; haue but a particuler charge, the generall primacy being reſerued to him who in the ſame ſucceedeth <hi>S. Peter</hi> who is the B. of Rome, and chiefe Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor. I ſayd that holy water, graynes, croſſes, hallowed images, Papal, and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopall bleſſings, the ſtations, diuerſity of habits, cords, leather girdles, viſiting Churches, and Altars, beades, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſions, and the like to be toyes; when as it ſufficiently appeareth, almoſt all of theſe thinges to be auncient and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed in the Catholicke Church, which vſe is to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinued, yea euen in thoſe things which are more freſh indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cements to piety &amp; deuotion. I affirmed
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:21656:16"/> that there were only two Sacraments, Baptiſme, and the Supper; whereas yet the Catholike Church lightned by the holy ghoſt, doth plainly teach &amp; define that there be ſeauen true Sacraments: all which, and what other hereſyes ſoeuer condemned by the Catholike Roman Church, I doe alſo condemne, and with firme faith belieue, hold, and profeſſe the contrary to theſe hereſies defined by the ſame: for it is moſt certayn, that in the decrees of the holy Roman Church, reaſon is not ſeuered from authority, &amp; the ſchoole doctrin eſpecially in articles religion, to be altogether conformable to the ſenſe, or doctrine of the holy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. This further I confeſſe, that I haue without cauſe complained in my books of the Court of Rome, as if it had vſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped authority belonging to others; for vnles that Church out of her lawfull authority ouer Archbiſhops &amp; Biſhops keep them both in order, the violating of all lawes will eaſely follow by their diſſenſion. It is truly the greateſt happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the Church, when her inferiour Paſtors vnder one moſt vigila<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Paſtour receaue and execute from him who hath
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:21656:16"/> ſupreme authority ouer all, reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of life, and the charge of ſound, and ſincere doctrine. And truly ſhould not the mild, and Fatherly care of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Inquiſition watch attentiuely ouer our Lords flocke, the ſcabbed ſheep would find no cure, and that moſt wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked infectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> would ſoone farre &amp; neere ſpread it ſelfe. The ordinary armour of that tribunall are ſound doctrine and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction full of charity, and not theſe others which I out of my exulcerated mind haue with ſo many falſityes, and ſlaunders exaggerated: but in caſe the feſtered ſoares doe not yield to lenitiue medicines, then is it both fit, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary that the Phiſitian apply more ſharp, and corroſiue plaiſters.</p>
            <p n="7">7. But now euen the inward fyre of the diſeaſes of my mynd did rage al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt by miracle, after the entrance of <hi>Gregory</hi> the fifteenth to the gouernment of the Church (whoſe emine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t piety, ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular wiſdome, and continuall ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of a moſt innocent life, I indeed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieued to haue aduaunced him to that high honour) I began to thinke of ſome more healthfull courſe, the holy ghoſt
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:21656:17"/> enlightning me with the beames of his grace, in ſo much that now the dangers of my ſoule in the ſtate I liued in, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganne to ſhew themſelues euery day more cleerly vnto me, and I now wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered that I had gone ſo farre in folly, and errour, that I would conioyne my ſelfe with them who were heretikes, &amp; playne, and abſolute ſciſmaticks. Such in tymes paſt was the guilefull deceite of a few <hi>Arrians</hi> in the Councell of <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini,</hi> that by ſecret colluſion they had as it were drawne almoſt all the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes into Arianiſme, <hi>tunc</hi> (ſayth <hi>S. Hierome</hi>) <note place="margin">Hieron. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Lucife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rianos.</note> 
               <hi>totus mundus ingemuit, &amp; miratus eſt ſe eſſe Arrianum,</hi> then all the world groaned, and merueyled to ſee it ſelfe become Arrian: ſo (alas) &amp; much worſe it befell me, that I ſaw, wondered, and lamented my ſelfe an heretike amongſt heretiks, &amp; ſciſmatick amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ſciſmaticks. And that the Engliſhmen co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>playne not of me that I doe them wrong, but that they may know my departure from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; return to my mother the holy Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Church to haue been lawful, &amp; for iuſt cauſe, I am conſtrained to lay open their hereſy, and ſchiſme with which it
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:21656:17"/> was no way co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenient, that I ſhould be further entangled or taynted.</p>
            <p n="8">8. In England (if we ſpeake of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion) are many ſects: there are Purita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, or rigid Caluiniſts: there are more mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate who call themſelues only Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, &amp; Reformed: there are Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts, &amp; thoſe deuided into diuers ſects: neither want there Arrians, Photinians &amp; ſuch like raffe of lewd me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who albeit they be not allowed openly to profeſſe their errours, yet are they not baniſhed the land, nor puniſhed at home, but are tolerated, whiles in the mean time they ſpread their poyſon, &amp; infect others: that the Anabaptiſts hold many hereſies none that is not an Anabaptiſt will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny but they in Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d freely haue their conuenticles, and his Maieſty himſelfe one day told me, that lately in London, at the aſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bly of the Anabaptiſts, a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man had made a ſermon, &amp; miniſtred their Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts. The hereſies of the Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritans are notorious, to wit, that there is no free will, God to be Author of ſinne, God merly, becauſe ſo it pleaſeth him to damn many; Chriſt not to haue dyed for al, to haue vndergon the puniſhment of hel, that infants baptized be da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned &amp;c. the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:21656:18"/> more moderate Proteſtants, although they goe about, touching points of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, to free themſelues in ſome ſort from hereſy, becauſe they doe not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit entirely the hereſies eyther of Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uin or Luther, if they follow the pure doctrine of the Engliſh Church, which they call Reformed; yet can they not ſo eſcape or rid their hands from Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans and Anabaptiſts with whome they fully communicate: and if any Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſt or Puritan come to their Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical Conuenticles, they neither auoid him, nor exclude him; yea almoſt all the Puritan Miniſters handle, and mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter the very Sacraments of the falſe En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Church vnto all commers, at leaſt vnto all Caluiniſts. And if <hi>Acacius</hi> of Conſtantinople, for that he had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated with <hi>Peter Mogge</hi> an heretick of Alexandria, &amp; if all the Eaſt Church for perſiſting in communion with <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius,</hi> was ſeparated by a long anathema or curſe from the Roman, and Weſt Church; how much more are the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants of England to be eſteemed for he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retikes, becauſe they continually com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate which heretikes; neyther do
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:21656:18"/> they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demne them; or deny them their company, but rather admit them al that will communicate in their ceremonies, rites, and Sacraments with the Engliſh Church? Doth not the deformed Church of England publickly and plainly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion, &amp; Eccleſiaſtical league or fryendſhip with Geneua the mother of Puritans, and all other forrayn Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiniſts? Are there not euen in London the Kinges Citty, and that by publicke graunt of the King, Churches of the French, Flemiſh and Italian Caluiniſts, which hate and abhorre the doctrine, profeſſion, &amp; rites of England, &amp; yet are moſt deerely beloued ſiſters of the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Synagogue? And by them Purita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſme is eſpecially maintayned, and ſet forward in Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. Moreouer with the Luthera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, polluted with very many he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies, the Engliſh Sinagogue is moſt ready to communicate, and labours all that it can, to the end that theſe mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſters of many heads may like Hercules hydra agree in one body, and a vnion (as they terme it) be made of all the reformed Churches: but of purging the faith and doctrine of theſe different ſects, &amp; roo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:21656:19"/> out their hereſies no care is had; &amp; yet the Lutherans hate the Sacramenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries <hi>cane peius, &amp; angue.</hi> Other hereſies of Engliſhmen concerning faith, &amp; good workes, and iuſtification, as alſo the B. Sacrament, priuate Maſſes, Merits of good workes, praying vnto Saints, worſhipping of holy Images, holy rites and ceremonyes, the ſoules of the depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and the like, which they out of an hereticall ſpirit doe condemne, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boliſh, and which I with the ſame ſpirit in part haue once condemned, and abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed, I meane not now further to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſe; ſomewhat (I meane as much as this place requires) I ſhall after touch, and more els where in a larger worke. I come to their ſchiſme.</p>
            <p n="9">9. Sure I am that the Engliſh Sect which the deformed Engliſh men call the Reformed Church, to be more deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, &amp; ſeparated from the Church truly Catholike then they are themſelues de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided from the whole world, <hi>diuiſos toto orbe Britannos.</hi> That they are perfectly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Roman Church, &amp; other Churches ſubiect thervnto, &amp; commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municating with the ſame in Religion
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:21656:19"/> and fayth, they will the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues willingly confeſſe, and the thing is moſt euident, moſt notorious. Now wheras the Roma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Church with the others aforſaid is truly &amp; properly according to the Cath. Faith, the Cath. Church of Chriſt, doth it not neceſſarily follow the Engliſh Church as they call it, to be cleane cut of fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Catholike Church, and conſequently that it is not the body of Chriſt, nor his houſe, nor, abſolutly ſpeaking, to be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a Church? Which when at length I plainly perceyued, I was no longer to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>emain therin. They will obiect, &amp; ſay, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s this now plain vnto thee, who yet in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hy book of Eccleſiaſtical co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wealth didſt ſtile Rome, Babylon, who diddeſt deny the Church of Rome, who didſt teach vs that it was properly ſchiſmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal; but that which thou affirmeſt of our Church doth not ſo plainly appeare vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs. So they. Wherfor I ſhal goe about to mak this point euident vnto the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh, who know ful well that I am not Pithagoras whoſe only authority amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g his ſchollers for any thing that he ſayd, was held for beſt proofe: let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be moued with thoſe things I haue
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:21656:20"/> ſayd, without other argument, yea fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther let my wordes want their weight, &amp; credit eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> where I bring my reaſons and proofes, if they be found to be weak and feeble. Truly my reaſon on which I relied, when I made Chriſtian <hi>Rome</hi> to be <hi>Babylon,</hi> was becauſe the propheſy o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>S. Iohn</hi> could no be explicated of <hi>Rom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> as it was heathen, before it imbraced the fayth of Chriſt. <note place="margin">Apocalip. 8.</note> But this reaſon is of no force; for albeyt that this were granted, yet it followeth not that the Chriſtian <hi>Rome</hi> is <hi>Babylon,</hi> for it is the opinion o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> many Catholik interpreters, that in the perſecution of Antichriſt, the heathen Idolaters, &amp; enemies of Chriſt are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps to ſubdue Rome; and that of them this propheſy not yet acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pliſhed may conueniently be vnderſtood: yet ſo, as the fayth of the Catholike Church ſtil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> continue ſafe, and ſound; by this inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation my affection of <hi>Rome</hi> as Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, is ouerthrown, and conteyns in i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a meer ſlau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der; for I know the Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Rome</hi> not to be <hi>Babylon,</hi> nor that it can without exceeding iniury be ſo called<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But God forbid that in this propheſy o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>Apocalyps,</hi> we ſhould conceaue th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:21656:20"/> 
               <hi>Roman</hi> Church it ſelfe the mother of all Churches, &amp; head of Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, hertofore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o haue been, or herafter that it ſhalbe <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ylon,</hi> for thoſe things which are ſpoken of the Citty, are not to be transferred or explicated of the Church. I denyed the Church to be at Rome, but proued it not, and therefore that deny all is to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>laced amongſt my curſes and raylings, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ea alſo amongſt my hereſyes, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y my ſelf refuting the ſame, by reaſon in my other workes, in which ſtrongly I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aue affirmed the Roman Church with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he others adherent to be the true &amp; on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y Catholike Church of Chriſt, &amp; now <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oe as much as I can profeſſe, &amp; auer the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ame. I ſayd that it had made a ſchiſme; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut then I ſayd it, when as yet I had no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>xact knowledge of ſchiſme or nature <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>herof, &amp; I erred groſſly herin, becauſe it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s a manifeſt falſity: the argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t brought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or the contrary is of no moment, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ludeth nothing; for he who being law <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ully made head of any body, &amp; doth ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ile and proclayme himſelfe, doth not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eperate himſelfe from the body, neither <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oth he caſt away the body from him, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut ioyneth himſelfe vnto it, which is
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:21656:21"/> a farr different thing from ſchiſme; but this I will further proſecute in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiew, &amp; correction of that worke: now only I declare how it is euident to me that the Engliſhmen, and much more a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Sectaryes of our age are truly, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly Schiſmaticks, for that without all lawfull cauſe they haue cut themſelues from the true Church of Chriſt, which is the Catholike Roman Church, &amp; all thoſe that communicate therewith.</p>
            <p n="10">10. Two cauſes only there may be of lawfull ſeparation, that one or more Churches of Chriſt, may wholy repell one or more Churches from their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municating with them, without the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curring of ſchiſme: the one is hereſy, the other ſchiſme it ſelfe. The heretical<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Churches that are incorrigible are to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> eſchewed of Catholikes, who are to hau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> no Eccleſiaſticall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> This is a point well knowne among<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Chriſtians. I often demaunded of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Engliſhmen why they ſeparated them<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelues from the Roman Church, takin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the ſame as it comprizeth all other beſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des that adhere therunto; was it for an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hereſy? But truly none of them al coul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:21656:21"/> eyther in writing, or by word of mouth ſhew eyther the Roman Catholikes of of our tymes, or our Predeceſſors, in their publick profeſſion to be, or haue been tainted with any true hereſy. The moſt ſoueraigne King of great Britaine playnly, and publickely graunted this vnto me: this the wiſer of their chiefe, and inferiour Miniſters graunted, and many other learned men affirmed the Church of Rome not to erre in the fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentall fayth: wherfore by the grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Engliſh Proteſtants this Church is not hereticall. They will obiect per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, the Church of Rome not to erre in the fundamentall fayth (which I in the booke of the cauſes of my departure, &amp; in the ſermon made at London ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to defend) but to erre, and to haue fallen into hereſy in other not funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall articles; but firſt of all I know not what article there is of true fayth which is not fundamentall: neyther could I euer conceaue, or were they able to explicate, how that diſtinction ſhould be admitted amongſt the articles of faith, that ſome were fundamentall, &amp; ſome not; for truly I alwayes iudged
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:21656:22"/> all and euery of thoſe articles which are truly to be fu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tal, but I erred in this that from the number of fundamentall, and conſequently from the true articles, I excluded many which are indeed ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of faith, and conſequently were all fundamentall, and cannot without hereſy be denyed, howſoeuer they be not of theſe principall, of the Trinity, Incarnation, Neceſſity of grace, Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing in the name of the Trinity &amp;c. as are the Sacraments, Iuſtification, the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of workes, merits, indulgences, and the like which before I ſet downe, as now defined by the Church, becauſe theſe no leſſe rely on Gods reuelation then the former, and therefore as much belong vnto faith as they, for he who makes God deceitfull in any one article whatſoeuer, he muſt neceſſarily ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg him to be deceiptfull in all the reſt: agayne I demaunded of ſuch as mea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſincerely that they would produce but one article, in which the Roman Church doth hold, and teach amiſſe: they are wont to vrge that of Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation of bread and wyne into the body, and bloud of Chriſt, out of which
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:21656:22"/> they gather certayne hereſies, to wit, Chriſt not to haue a true body, but a fa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſticall one, becauſe we put the whole body in ſo litle a compaſſe, or quantity of bread, in ſo much ſay they, as the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy is no more a body: again, that Chriſt is not in heauen if he be on the altar on earth, againſt the article of his Aſcenſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: finally Chriſt not to haue beene borne of the <hi>Virgin Mary,</hi> becauſe that we doe make him of bread. In theſe men truly that is veryfyed which <hi>S. Hierom</hi> writes, <note place="margin">In Epiſt. ad Titum c. 3.</note> 
               <hi>nullum eſſe Schiſma quod non ſibi aliquam hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſim confingat, vt meritò ab Eccleſia receſſiſſe videatur.</hi> There is no ſchiſme which fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes not to it ſelfe ſome hereſy, that it may ſeeme with ſome reaſon to haue departed from the Church. And as for Tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſubſtantiation which the Catholiks teach, that is moſt far fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe hereſies, for in this all the properties of a body are out of danger from being deſtroyed, although we graunt the ſame body to be conteyned vnder neuer ſo little for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes and accidents of bread: albeit theſe propertyes <hi>in ordine ad locum,</hi> as they are referred to place, which is a thing extrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecall to the body, may by Gods power
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:21656:23"/> be ſeparated, which thing is fully expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated by the ſchoole Doctors; but what hereſy can they imagine in vs, if we doe al conſtantly affirme that we belieue as an article of fayth, Chriſt to haue had &amp; ſtill to haue a true body with all natural propertyes, in it ſelfe, which propertyes we belieue &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe by the ſame omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pote<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t power may be preſerued although the body be reduced to neuer ſo litle an external place; neither can any by The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logical proofe infring the ſame: humane Philoſophy neither can, nor muſt mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure Gods power, let that iudge what can be done by nature, but thoſe things that are aboue nature, let it reuerence, but not iudge: neyther doth it follow hence, Chriſts body not to be in heauen but on the altar: we all by diuine fayth belieue Chriſt haue aſcended into hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and there for euer to ſit at the right hand of his father; notwithſtanding we affirme that by diuine power one and the ſelfe ſame body may be in many places at once, at leaſt ſacramentally, and this cannot be impugned, but only out of humane Philoſophy, and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming arguments: and laſtly we ſay not
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:21656:23"/> the body to be made of bread, as if it had not beene before, but we hould the bread to be tranſubſtantiated into the body of Chriſt, which body did preexiſt, or was before the conſecrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and before tranſubſtantiation, the body of Chriſt borne of the <hi>Virgin Mary</hi> is extant and exiſtent, into which the bread is tranſubſtantiated; truly theſe men do ignorantly forge theſe hereſies, for he is an heretick who directly vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters hereſy: but if they aske of vs what we belieue of the truth of Chriſtes body, of the Aſcenſion, of the Incarnation, they ſhall heare vs deliuer the true, and Catholike beliefe, notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding that we affirme other things out of which they imagine to follow theſe erroneous opinions, which we vtterly, and truly deny to follow of them, and they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not Theologically conuince vs to the contrary. In ſo much then as pertaineth vnto hereſy, they can pretend no cauſe wherefore they haue iuſtly, &amp; for good cauſe ſeparated the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our Church, therfor they made an vnlawful ſchiſme.</p>
            <p n="11">11. The more moderate Engliſh Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts that are not Purita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, vrge not much
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:21656:24"/> the hereſy of the Roman Church, nor from that ground free themſelues from the foule ſpot of ſchiſme, but they vrge fiercely idolatry, and obtruding of new articles of fayth, by which meanes they will haue the Roman, that is the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Church, to haue fallen from the true faith, and hereby chiefely they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the equity of their ſeparation; this idolatry they will haue to conſiſt in the worſhip, &amp; inuocation of Saints, and reuerence of Relikes, and Images, and moſt of all in the Adoration of the B. Sacrament: &amp; a more ſecret Idolatry they will haue to lye lurking in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence we repoſe on ſalt, water, oyle, and other thinges exorciſed &amp; bleſſed: they alſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plain of new articles thruſt vpon them by Catholikes, in the defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitions of the Councell of Trent, about Iuſtification, Workes, Merits, Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, Indulgences, and the like; but all in vayn. Certainly if we Catholikes were indeed Idolaters, we ſhould not only be heretickes, but much worſe then moſt heretickes, &amp; therefore ought to be auoyded, and altogether ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted far from all the faithfull. And I wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:21656:24"/> how any man that is in his right wits, can charge them with idolatry, who dayly profeſſe themſelues to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue in one God, and for this ground, or foundation of fayth are ready to ſhed their bloud; who dayly preach and teach that no diuine worſhip can be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to any pure Creature. This then is a baſe ſlaunder. Are we for our inuoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of Saints, worſhipping of images, adoration of the B. Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t held guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty or ſuſpected with theſe men of ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry? Let them ſeeke, let them vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, let them penetrate what we hold of the vnity of the true God, what of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine honour not to be imparted vnto creatures, and then they ſhall preſently perceaue all ſuch to be very Sots, who iudge and affirme vs to be idolaters, that is worſhippers of creatures with diuine honour; neither let them breake out in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to open ſchiſme, vntill they haue found in our doctrine and practiſe, true Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try.</p>
            <p n="12">12. No Catholike euer auouched dead men, or Angells to be worſhipped with diuine honour; we are not ſuch fooles. <hi>Vigilantius</hi> in tymes paſt obiected
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:21656:25"/> this vnto the Catholikes, but falſely as <hi>S. Hier.</hi> writing againſt him doth ſhew: and in this as in other thinges of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, we haue the ancient Fathers, our good maiſters, from them we doe not diſſent, we doe not depart, we doe not diſagree: we willingly imbrace &amp; moſt exactly practiſe their moſt hole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome doctrine, and euery way Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, touching the worſhiping of Saints <hi>Originis lib.</hi> 8. <hi>contra Celſum. Epiphanij hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſ.</hi> 79. <hi>August. Epist.</hi> 44. <hi>&amp; libro de quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titate animae cap.</hi> 34. <hi>&amp; lib. de vera relig. cap.</hi> 55. <hi>&amp; contra Fauſtum lib.</hi> 23. <hi>cap.</hi> 21. <hi>Cyrilli Alexand. lib.</hi> 6. <hi>contra Iulianum. Theodoreti in hiſtoria Sa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ctorum Patrum cap.</hi> 21. I cite not the wordes of theſe, and other Fathers becauſe the ſhortnes of this ſmal treatiſe doth not comport it. From whence then haue theſe late blind mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters borrowed their new eyes, when as the Catholike Church long ere they were born was moſt excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly furniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with moſt reſplendent, moſt ſecure, &amp; ſhining la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ps of learning &amp; ſanctity?</p>
            <p n="13">13. Feſtiual daies belong vnto the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of Saints, which we celebrate in their remembrance, prayſing God and
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:21656:25"/> thanking him, that he hath aduaunced mortal men, and ſinners to ſo high a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of holines: neither is this a late no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelty in the Church by annuall deuotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to keep feſtiuall daies in the honour of Saintes; it is an ancient vſe, (and ſo an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient that it may well be referred to the traditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Apoſtles) that beſides the So<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>day, the birth-daies of Saintes ſhould be kept holy; which thing I ſee appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by the ancie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t cuſtom of the Church. I find <hi>S. Cyprian</hi> very careful to haue the dayes noted, <note place="margin">Lib. 3. Ep. 6.</note> in which the Chriſtians were martired, <hi>vt talibus</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>celebre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur hic à nobis oblationes, &amp; ſacrificia ob co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morationes ipſoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> that on thoſe daies they ſuffred we in remembra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of them may celebrate here the oblatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, &amp; ſacrifices. <hi>S. Iohn Chryſoſtome,</hi> &amp; <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> exhort the faithful to the due obſeruance of the feaſtes of Saints. <note place="margin">Chryſoſt. ſerm. in martyrem Pelagiam. Augu. in Pſal. 88. part. 2. in fine.</note> Wherfore I cannot but exceedingly merueil at the new ſcruples of Proteſtants, not ſoberly <note n="*" place="margin">So the Proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts tranſlate <hi>non plus ſapere qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> oportet ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere, ſed ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere ad ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brietatem.</hi> Rom. 12.3</note> but more highly thinkinge of themſelues then they ought, whiles they haue fully iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, and taught all feaſtes of the Saints, yea of the <hi>B. Virgin</hi> mother of God, of the Apoſtles, and moſt famous martirs to be
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:21656:26"/> abrogated and taken away, albeyt the Engliſh Proteſtants, be not ſo rigorous; for in this matter they haue left ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what to remayn as before, though it be very little.</p>
            <p n="14">14. To inuocate Saints departed, ſay theſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, is nothing els the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to make many Gods, and this our calling vpon them, and worſhipping of their images not to differ fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the cuſtomes of Pagans, vnder which pretext they abhorre and auoid vs all they can: but for vs it were eaſy (if this place would beare ſo long diſpute) to beate backe, and refell all theſe ſlaunders of heretikes: for they are forced, if they beleeue the Scriptures, to admit this; (as certayn that the ſoules of the Saints with God pray for vs mortall men, and that not in generall only, but alſo in particuler, and it is moſt euident in this life the faithfull to be holpen by the prayers of the vertuous;) for <hi>Moyſes</hi> often by his prayers turned away the wrath of God from the people of Iſrael, <note place="margin">Iob 42.18.</note> and God exhorted the friends of <hi>Iob</hi> to intreate his prayers, thereby to obteyne pardon for their folly. <note place="margin">Eph. 6. Coloſſ. 4. 1. Theſ. 5. 2. Theſ. 3. Hebr. 13. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>S. Paul</hi> ofter co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended himſelfe to the prayers of the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:21656:26"/> faithful: &amp; theſe men may learne if they liſt, the Saints, whoſe ſoules liue in the the ſight of God, and raign with Chriſt, to pray for ſuch as are yet liuing in the militant Church, out of Hieremy Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiell, and the Apocalips. <note place="margin">Hierem. 15 Ezech. 14. Apocalip. 5.8. &amp; 8.</note> That for their ſakes God graunteth many fauours vnto them, they haue in the ſame holy Scriptures, and that in many places, as <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 26.4.5.24. <hi>Exodus</hi> 32.13. 3. <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gum</hi> 18.36. 1. <hi>Paralip.</hi> 29.18. 3. <hi>Reg.</hi> 11.12.32.34. <hi>&amp;</hi> 15.4. 4. <hi>Reg.</hi> 8.19. <hi>&amp;</hi> 19.34. and 20.6. and <hi>Iſa.</hi> 37.35. See the commentaries which are ſayd to be <hi>S. Chryſoſtomes,</hi> in the ſecond <hi>Homily</hi> vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the 50. <hi>Pſalme.</hi> Chriſt warneth vs to make fryends of the mammon of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, <note place="margin">Luke 16.</note> 
               <hi>Vt cum defeceritis recipiant vos in aeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na tabernacula,</hi> that when you fayle, they receyue you into their euerlaſting taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacles: <note place="margin">Auguſt. de ciuitate Dei lib. 21. c. 7. Gen. 28.12. Heb. 1.14.</note> out of this place <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buteth much to the interceſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Saints.</p>
            <p n="15">15. This interceſſion of Saints the holy Fathers acknowledg, admit, and confirme<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And truly of Angels the Lad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of <hi>Iacob,</hi> and their other employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for vs are notorious. See <hi>Origen contra Celſum lib.</hi> 8. Of the Angells atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:21656:27" rendition="simple:additions"/> vpon vs, ſee <hi>S. Auguſtine;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Aug. Epi. 122.</note> and of our guardian Angell the Scriptures doe often, and plainly make mention, <note place="margin">Gen. 48. Exod. 23. Pſalm. 33. Math. 18. Actor. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and the Fathers alſo moſt cleerely. <note place="margin">Nyſſenus in vita Moyſis. Baſil. in Pſal. 33. Hieron in 18. Mat.</note> If there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore euery man haue to aſſiſt, and guard him an Angell of our Lord, what ſhall hinder but that he may craue his help? I heard once in Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, with great guſt one of my fellow Chanons of <hi>Windeſor</hi> preaching before the King, and affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming roundly in his ſermon that he ſaw no reaſon to the contrary, why euery faythful man might not turne, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert himſelfe towards his good Angell, and ſay, <hi>Sancte Angele cuſtos ora pro me,</hi> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly guardian Angell pray for me. Of the interceſſion of Angells, &amp; their labours for our helpe, and benefit, any one beſides the former may alſo reade theſe Fathers, <hi>S. Anton. Monachorum Parentem Epiſt.</hi> 2. <hi>ad Arſeonitas, Anaſtaſium Synaitam in Hexam. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>Antiochum Abbat. Hom.</hi> 61. <hi>Chryſost. de incomprehenſib. Dei natura. Hom.</hi> 3. <hi>&amp; Hom in Martyres Aegyptios. Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron. in Epiſt.</hi> 1. <hi>Cyrill. Alexandrinum apud Anaſtaſium Nycaenum quaest.</hi> 61. <hi>Theodoretu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ibidem. Damaſcen. Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Paraleſ. cap.</hi> 7. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="16">16. For Interceſſion of Saints, we
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:21656:27"/> haue the common conſent of the aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Fathers. See <hi>S. Cyprian Lib. de mortalitate. Hieron. aduerſus Vigilantium. August. de Baptiſmo. Lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 7. <hi>&amp; Lib.</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. <hi>&amp; de verbis Apost. Sermo.</hi> 47. <hi>&amp; Sermon.</hi> 46. <hi>de Sanctis. &amp; Lib.</hi> 9. <hi>Confeſſ. cap.</hi> 3. <hi>&amp; Lib. de cura pro mortuis agenda cap.</hi> 16. <hi>&amp; contra Fauſtum Lib.</hi> 20. <hi>cap.</hi> 21. <hi>&amp; in Meditatio. c.</hi> 20. <hi>Leo Magnus Sermon. de Sancto Laurentio. Gaudentius Brixian. Serm.</hi> 17. <hi>Gregorius Magnus lib.</hi> 7. <hi>Indictione</hi> 2. <hi>Epist.</hi> 25. <hi>Bernard. in Cantic. Serm.</hi> 77. I pretermit innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable others of later tymes: the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures therefore, and Fathers, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the vniuerſall Church doe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curely warrant vs, that the Angells and ſoules of Saints departed this life, doe pray for the liuing, and that alſo in particular. Why then ſhould not eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry faythfull man take courage to inuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, or call vpon them whome moſt certainly he knowes to pray for him in heauen?</p>
            <p n="17">17. That the Inuocation of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels &amp; Saints, to the end that they pray for vs, and ioyne their prayers with ours, as <hi>S. Chryſostome</hi> ſpeaketh, <note place="margin">Serm. in Sanctum Meletium.</note> cannot
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:21656:28"/> be doubted of, is moſt euident; and of the <hi>B. Virgin</hi> Mother of God a part, that ſhe is to be inuocated by vs, that ſhe pray for vs to her ſonne, we haue moſt eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent teſtimonyes <hi>Iraeneus lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 19. <hi>Athanaſ in Euang. de Deipara: Nazianzen orat. in Cyprianum. Baſilius Seleuciae orat</hi> 1. <hi>de verbo incarnato. Auguſt. ſermo</hi> 1. <hi>de Annun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciatione. Coſmas Hieroſolym. &amp; Sophronius item Hieroſolymitanus orat.</hi> 6. <hi>de Angelorum excellentia<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Hildefonſus Toletanus &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="18">18. Now for the Inuocation of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Saints, beſides, the ſacred Virgin, that the moſt auncient practice of the Church doth ſo much as I ſayd before, it appertaineth to the tradition of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, for this inuocation hath alwaies beene in vſe, and neuer reproued by any who was not held for an heretike. It were to long a labour to recount the Fathers who inuocate Saints, or teach them to be inuocated; that, elſewhere I haue aboundantly performed. And this perpetuall cuſtome of the Church of Inuocating Saints, that they pray for vs, and help vs with their prayers, was neuer ſo much as found fault withall, but rather the contrary errour was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:21656:28"/> by <hi>S. Hierome</hi> in <hi>Vigilantius,</hi> which conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the whole Church allowed, and therefore our new <hi>Vigilantians</hi> are to be condemned by the iudgement of the whole Church, whoſe temerity in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king our Inuocation to be idolatry is very ſingular; neyther haue theſe Vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantians any thing of moment that they can oppoſe: their obiections I haue elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where fully refuted, and I thinke that in another worke I haue fully defended the reuerent regard of holy Reliques, which God himſelfe, as moſt pleaſing vnto him, hath confirmed by moſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt miracles.</p>
            <p n="19">19. But our Aduerſaryes bouldly affirme, that in worſhipping of holy images, we commit idolatry: and from hence they will haue their departure fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs to be lawfull: but this alſo is a moſt vayn pretext of theirs: neyther can they thereby free themſelues from the infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous note of moſt filthy ſchiſme; for in caſe we honour images with a proper, &amp; peculiar honour, &amp; worſhip, which is exhibited to the thing it ſelfe repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented by the image, that is not ſupreme honour and worſhip, nor that true ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:21656:29"/> which alone is due vnto God; whereas therefore we doe moſt playn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly profeſſe diuine honour and ſupreme worſhip, not to be due, eyther vnto Saynts, or to their Reliques, &amp; much leſſe to their Images, why doe they obiect Idolatry vnto vs? The vſe of Images belongs to Eccleſiaſticall rites, and in theſe the ſure, certayne, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible rule to know, whether they be lawfull, and to be approued, is the practiſe, and vſe eſpecially of the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitiue Church: In ſo much as they are to be eſteemed good, and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full rytes, which eyther the Apoſtles, or ſome Apoſtolicall men haue or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayned, or haue eyther ſilently, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly approued; and it is moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, yea moſt vncontrollable, the Chriſtian Church euen moſt auncient, whole, and vniuerſall, with ioynt, and ſingular conſent, without all oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or contradiction, to haue reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renced, or worſhipped holy Images, eyther paynted or kerued. <hi>S. Iohn Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſcen</hi> hath collected in his three Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions which he wrote for Images moſt aboundant teſtimonyes. The Fathers
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:21656:29"/> of the ſeauenth Generall Councell haue done the like: and after theſe many others of our Church: What igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant companion then dare condemne that which the moſt holy, and moſt learned Fathers haue commaunded, haue taught, haue practized? that which the Catholike Church, taught by the Apoſtles, hath alwayes obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued? that which God himſelfe by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miracles hath confirmed? Are they not then, accordinge to the verdict of S. <hi>Augustine,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Auguſt. Epiſt. 118.</note> moſt inſolent mad men, who retayne not the vſe of Images, nor deuoutly keepe them with that pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar honour, due vnto them (ſo as the ſupreme be not giuen them) but rather abuſe, prophane, and ſacrilegiouſly caſt them away?</p>
            <p n="20">20. Two thinges eſpecially, doe our Aduerſaryes vrge agaynſt this our worſhippinge of holy Images, by which they contend, that we cannot auoyd this charge of Idolatry, and by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he ſame they ground themſelues in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heir ſchiſme, as if it were lawful. One is Gods co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement, which forbiddeth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll Images to be made; the other that
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:21656:30"/> they cannot be excuſed from true exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall idolatry who adore the true God in any exteriour ſigne that is a meere creature. Theſe men with Caluin will haue the golden calfe to haue beene vſed by the children of Iſrael to repreſent the true God: and in this aboue all others doth <hi>Reynolds</hi> the Engliſh Puritan ſettle and ground his Treatiſe of the Idolatry of the Roma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Church: but with me there is no doubt, neyther can there be with our aduerſaries, but the moſt auncient Fathers, and Catholike Church to haue known the ten Commandements, and the hiſtory of the Calf, and yet without all difficulty, and ſcruple they vſed ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Images with honour and reuerence: but neyther doth this diſputation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeme this ſhort diſcourſe, the tyme wil come when I ſhal haue opportunity to to refute this booke of <hi>Reynolds</hi> Of the Idolatry of the Church of Rome, on which England doth moſt of all main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayn her ſchiſme. Now to deale briefely<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I call to their remembrance the doings of <hi>Salomon,</hi> who endewed with diuine wiſdome, not only adorned his temple with thoſe Images and workes of art
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:21656:30"/> which God had cauſed to be made, as were the Cherubims &amp;c. but added of him ſelfe, ſo many ſhapes and kerued pictures of trees and beaſtes, as we read in Scripture, <note place="margin">3. Reg. 10. 19. 20.</note> for there were brazen Oxen, Palmes, Pomegranats &amp;c. and his Throne he ſet out with great, &amp; little golden Lyons. Doubtles <hi>Salomon</hi> vnderſtood this commaundement of not making Images, &amp; hath by his own fact explicated the ſame vnto vs ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently, to wit, that it was not comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for all tymes, nor that it was of the diuine natural law (but ſo farre forth as it denyed ſupreme worſhip to be giuen vnto them) but only of the diuine po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitiue law Temporall, and Conditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, then and ſo long to be obſerued, when and how long there ſhould be danger leaſt the picture ſhould be cauſe and occaſion of Idolatry: wherfore ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in vs now ſo well inſtructed, there is no danger of committing idolatry by Images, that prohibition of the law which forbiddeth pictures to be made, hath no place with vs; and therefore the Image-breakers aboliſhing the vſe of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages, breaking them in peeces, and
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:21656:31"/> vnworthily handling the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, haue alwaies been eſteemed of the Church, &amp; held for moſt wicked hereticks, &amp; nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bred amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the enemies of Chriſtian Religion.</p>
            <p n="21">21. The children of Iſrael in adoring the Calfe to haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted Idolatry, is a thing moſt euident; neither will I euer grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, that this Calfe repreſented to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the true God; &amp; it is moſt falſe &amp; againſt the true ſenſe of the Scripture to ſay, the Iſraelites in that Calf to haue adored the true God; they adored the ſame golden Calfe, which they erring moſt beaſtly, thought to haue had in it the diuinity of the true God: this as I hope in due place, &amp; time I ſhal co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uince out of moſt cleere paſſages of the holy Scripture, &amp; ſhal re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute the light argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of <hi>Caluin</hi> &amp; <hi>Rey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nolds,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Latria.</note> &amp; ſhew the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that God himſelfe may be adored with higheſt honour in cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral ſignes, without al danger of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting Idolatry: and that the Engliſh rely on a moſt filthy errour, whiles they dreame out of <hi>Reynolds</hi> follyes, to triu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ph ouer the Roman Church, as if it were truly Idolatricall, &amp; therfore by them lawfully reiected, and forſaken. In our vſe of holy Images, wheras euery ill cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:21656:31"/> &amp; all ſcandall are ordinarily wanting, becauſe we lyue not amongſt Idolaters, and are, or may be well in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed touching the lawfull worſhip of Images, moſt farre off from the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme worſhip giuen vnto God, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we may lawfully kneele before an Image, and ſo adore the perſon repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented therby with ſupreme honour, in caſe he be capable therof. So did the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Iſrael adore God in the cloud at the gate of the tabernacle, <note place="margin">Exod. 33.</note> but they ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red not the cloud; lykewiſe in the fyre: <note place="margin">2. Paralip. 7.3.</note> neyther did they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit idolatry, whiles they adored God in theſe corporal ſigns: ſuch therfore as conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne this adoration, as of it ſelf purly &amp; properly idolatrical, haue not in them ſo much as one dra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me of a pure, &amp; ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d Deuine. In vain therfor doe the Proteſtants co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plaine of this Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, that they may defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d their ſchiſme, &amp; in this very thing firſt of al they defile themſelues with hereſy, &amp; further they remaine true Schiſmatikes, becauſe there was no lawful cauſe of their ſeparation.</p>
            <p n="22">22. They obiect vnto vs a moſt cleere Idolatry, or bread-worſhip in the adoration of the B. Sacrament of the
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:21656:32"/> Altar, and by this alſo they ſeeke to excuſe themſelues from ſinne; but they are fowly miſtaken: for to vs the real &amp; corporall preſence of the body, &amp; bloud of our Lord Ieſus-Chriſt in the ſacred myſteries of the Euchariſt, is moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayn, and vndoubted; we adore the ſame body of Chriſt, capable of it ſelfe by reaſon of the hypoſtaticall vnion with the Word of ſupreme honour, ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hidden vnder theſe formes of bread, and wine; but hereof I cannot much diſpute in this place. This reall and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall preſence we ſuppoſe, and this ſuppoſall by our fayth is certayn, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we take it from the goſpell, Chriſt ſaying when he had bread in his hands, <hi>Hoc est corpus meum,</hi> this is my body, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the promiſe he had made ſaying, <note place="margin">Ioan. 6.</note> 
               <hi>Panis quem ego dabo caro mea est:</hi> the bread which I will giue is my body and therefore our aduerſaryes cannot ſuſpect that in this adoration we are ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able vnto the errour of idolatry, and ſo neither from this can they pretend any excuſe for their ſchiſme, but they are tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and properly not only ſchiſmatiks, but alſo heretiks, and therefore I was
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:21656:32"/> to depart from amongſt them, and no longer to adhere vnto their errours.</p>
            <p n="23">23. Beſides the former, they obiect vnto vs a certayn hidden or ſecret ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, when after the Exorciſmes, and bleſſings, we place a ſpirituall confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in ſalt, in water, in oyle, and the like: all which they heape together out of a deſyre to ſlaunder vs, and that they may ſeeme by any meanes to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe their ſchiſme: but they know full well, that we place no certayn confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in theſe things, as if we taught theſe creatures to receaue any certayn, and infallible force from our exorciſmes and prayers: theſe things we ſay are Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentalls, but not Sacraments, and hallowed to the end we may ſtirre vp our deuotion by them: all our confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence is placed in God alone, who mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by the prayers of the Church, euen by theſe creatures, by vertue of the ſame prayers &amp; bleſſings, beſtowes his guifts vppon vs: the greateſt part of thoſe and the like rites the Church hath receaued from Apoſtolicall tradition, and from ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of the moſt ancient Church, which who ſo followes cannot erre, &amp;
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:21656:33"/> he who contemnes, and caſts away, is himſelfe to be caſt forth as a raſh man, and enemy of the Church. Tertullian ſets down the vſe of holy Oyle: <note place="margin">Tertul. li. de Baptiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo.</note> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the matters of the Sacraments S. <hi>Augustine</hi> reckons Oyle. <note place="margin">Aug. Ep. 119.</note> The hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing of the water of Baptiſme hath been obſerued from tyme out of mind; for S. <hi>Cyprian</hi> makes mention of the hallowing of water, and oyle, and of Vnction alſo. <note place="margin">Cyprian. li. 1. Epist. vltima.</note> The holy Churches, I meane the materiall, in caſe by any chaunce they ſhould be defiled, were wont to be cleanſed by exorciſme, and waſhing of the walls: this we haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered by <hi>Optatus Mileuitanus.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Optatus Mileu. lib. 2. con. Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menian.</note> S. <hi>Baſill</hi> alſo from tradition deduceth the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ryte of annoyntinge with oyle the party that was baptized: <note place="margin">Baſil. lib. de Spiritu ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cto cap. 27</note> all anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity doth further teach vs the ſigne of the Croſſe to haue beene vſed in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery bleſſing and conſecration: <hi>Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus quaestione</hi> 118. <hi>Nazianzen Orat.</hi> 1. <hi>in Iulian. &amp; Orat. in funere Patris. Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſostom. Hom.</hi> 55. <hi>in Matthaeum. Auguſtin. tract.</hi> 118. <hi>in Ioan. &amp; ſermo. de tempore,</hi> 181. <hi>cap.</hi> 3. <hi>Areopagita &amp; alij.</hi> There are perhapps ſome rytes now vſed in the
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:21656:33"/> Church not ſo auncient, in which we vſe thinges bleſſed, and conſecrated; but as the primitiue Church, taught by the Apoſtles, neuer feared any da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger of ſecret Idolatry if it vſed co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſecrated oyle and the lyke, why ſhould we now feare who attribute no more to theſe new co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated things, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> antiquity attributed vnto the other? For theſe things to fly to Schiſme, is ſupreme impiety: theſe rytes are good, moſt of them were inſtituted by the Apoſtles, others haue had their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning from the deuotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Catholike Churches, no way co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to Faith, yea moſt conforme &amp; agreeing therunto: the variety of rites and ceremonyes was in auncient tyme in Churches, and yet none vnder that pretence did depart fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mutuall communion amongeſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues: <hi>The Auncients</hi> (ſayth Sozomen) <note place="margin">Sozomen lib. 7. c. 19<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>did worthily iudge yt a friuolous, or foolish matter, that they for cuſtome ſake should be ſeparated from one another, who in the chiefe points of Religion did agree;</hi> therefore this ſeparation of the Engliſhmen is friuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, yea raſh, and wicked, by which they haue deuided themſelues from the true Catholike Church, and haue
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:21656:34"/> broken forth without cauſe into open ſchiſme, with whom to communicate in diuine things, is to conſent to their moſt vniuſt, and pernicious ſchiſme.</p>
            <p n="24">24. Touching the new articles of which they make their complaynt and excuſe their ſchiſme, I wil not now diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute. I ſhould be too prolixe if I ſhould now turne aſide to theſe pointes in due place to be handled: only here I dema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whether they thinke theſe new articles (as they call them) to be contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry vnto fayth or not. If they were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to fayth, they ſhould be hereſies; and they would make the maintayners hereticks, and worthily to be deteſted, and ſeparated from the communion of all Catholike Churches. But I haue now proued that there is no hereſy in the Church of Rome; the moſt ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raygne King of great Britanny, &amp; very many learned men in that kingdome confeſſing, that the Church of Rome ſtands entier in the fundamentall faith; but I haue ſhewed before that there is no true Article that it not fundamental, and with aſſured fayth to be beleeued; therefore it hath no articles, which are
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:21656:34"/> contrary to the Catholike fayth, and in caſe they be not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to the true faith but contayn the ſame, they can yield no occaſion of ſchiſme. But (ſay they) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we reiect, and refuſe theſe articles, the Church of Rome hath ſeparated, &amp; cut vs of from that body. Truly I lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and bewayle theſe men to haue made a beaſtly, and perfect ſchiſme, before any thing was done, or defined concerning thoſe which they call new Articles, in much as they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not without exceeding vanity couer their ſchiſme by theſe new articles, for the effect cannot goe before the cauſe. I endeauour to ſhew that they made a ſchiſme without cauſe, &amp; hence I knew them to be true ſchiſmatiks, and for that I departed from them. And fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, theſe very Articles which they call new, can euidently be demonſtrated out of the Scriptures, tradition, and Fathers: and the contrary decreed by themſelues to be conuinced of open hereſy, if we will follow the iudgement of Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; howſoeuer ſome latter Proteſtants taking a more mild, &amp; moderate courſe are wont to bring for ſome poynt ſuch fauourable explications (of which my
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:21656:35"/> ſelfe haue heard many) as they ſeemed not to differ much from the Catholicke opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; theſe ſeeme to admit ſome pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous agreeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t; who then without per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious errour, yea true hereſy, wil place his ſaluation on only Faith, and exclude the neceſſity of Good works? Who will abſolutely deny our Merits, and that iuſt men cannot looſe their grace, and that they are impeccable, and cannot ſinne? And ſuch as ſtiffly hould theſe, and the like to be Articles of fayth, and the contrary to be hereſies, they vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly doe erre in matters of fayth, and ſhew themſelues to be heretiks, and conſequently to be well and worthily by the Catholike definitions placed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt ſuch: no hereſy therefore of the Church of Rome, no Idolatry open, or hidden, could giue occaſion to the ſchiſme of Proteſtants. Neither can they obiect Schiſme to the ſame Catholike Church, for it hath made no ſchiſme, but ſuffered it. From her hath <hi>Luther,</hi> from her <hi>Caluin,</hi> from her haue their firſt followers ſeparated themſelues, whiles ſtubbornly they refuſed to ſtand to her iudgement; theſe haue made a ſchiſme,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:21656:35"/> theſe haue deuided the garme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Chriſt, theſe haue erected altar againſt Altar, &amp; finally theſe haue left, and forſaken the Catholike Church.</p>
            <p n="25">25. Beſides the former alleadged, and diſcuſſed cauſes, they pretend an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other of Reformation, forſooth, needful to be made: but I amongeſt them ſcant euer ſaw any reformation, or to ſpeake more truly, ſaw none at all: but as for Deformations, I ſaw many amongſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For the moſt part, all care of conſcience is caſt away, they are not there (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting a very few of them) troubled with any ſcruples for adulteries, robbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes, or deceauing theyr neighbours; and in like manner for cooſenage, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceypts, and vſuries, for they haue wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedly aboliſhed auricular Confeſſion, faſting, pennance, and the like holy meanes for our amendment; and if theſe men had found amongſt vs ſomewhat amiſſe, in conuerſation, in actions, in gouernement, in direction, and the like, that had not argued any defect of the Church, but the errours of particuler men, which of Catholikes are not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed but myſliked: neyther for theſe
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:21656:36"/> leſſer a matters, as manners of life, and that not in all but ſome, were they to to make this moſt vgly ſchiſme. There remaines in the Roman Church a ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, an immoueable, and conſtant founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: and ſuppoſe it were true, <note place="margin">1. Cor. 3.</note> that we buylt thereon wood, ſtubble, hay; yet were we not therby debarred from ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation: but the Proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts haue depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from the foundatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it ſelf, they haue forſaken it, and except they build vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the foundatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which is Chriſt, gold ſiluer, &amp; pretious ſtones, which fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they boaſt to be theirs, all are <hi>proiecta viliora alga,</hi> waſt weedes, all fruiteles la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, and nothing auay leable to ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. There is one fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dation, not two, one Church not two, one Chriſt not two: if Chriſt be our fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dation (which they cannot deny) he is not certaynly theirs, they haue made themſelues a new Church, deuided and ſeparated from ours, and that alſo cannot be a Church, becauſe the Church is one not two, he who wilbe of their Church, he muſt needes be out of the true Church of Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="26">26. I confeſſe that I was deceaued
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:21656:36"/> by the Engliſh Proteſtants, before I had conſidered diligently the nature of ſchiſme; for when I obiected this fault vnto them, ſome of them replyed, that it was not their fault that they commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated not with the Church of Rome, who were ready to make vnion, and accorde; but that the Pope would not receaue them into communion, whom he had cut of from him and his, by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. This excuſe for a while ſeemed vnto me lawfull, and reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; yet when afterwards vppon this ground I beganne in priuate diſputes, and publick ſermons to vrge an vnion, which I tooke not to be farre off from making, and whiles I ſtriued to put my finger deeper into this feſtered vlcer, I perceaued in England, not the Engliſh Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſion which they commended vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me as modeſt, but the Confeſſion of <hi>Caluin,</hi> and many doting dreames of <hi>Luther,</hi> to be the common rule of their fayth: this I perceaued more clearely by the counterfeyt Synod of Proteſtants at <hi>Dort,</hi> in the which the opinions of the rigid <hi>Caluiniſts,</hi> by conſent, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence of the Engliſh ſect, by their
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:21656:37"/> miniſters ſent thither, were confirmed: which opinions of the rigid Puritans, if the confeſſion of the Engliſh Church, deuided into certain Articles, doe not as they pretend, include; then why vnder the name of the Engliſh Profeſſion, did the aforeſayd Miniſters yield their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and ſet their hands to theſe Calui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian exceſſes? How can it be that thoſe who profeſſe themſelues moſt eager e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies of the Church of Rome, ſhould be thought to deſire vnio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with the ſame Church, and the defect thereof not to proceed from their fault? How can they caſt the fault of their ſchiſme vppon the <hi>Tridentine</hi> excommunications, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore theſe <hi>Anathema's,</hi> had deuided them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues by ſchiſme from the Catholicke Church; and truly by a ſchime in ſome ſort farre more worſe, and foule, then was the ſchiſme made by <hi>Luther,</hi> and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter confirmed by the inſtigation of <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uin?</hi> Becauſe England in the begining refrayned from the opinions of <hi>Luther,</hi> and <hi>Caluin,</hi> and charged not the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Church with hereſy or Idolatry, as Lutherans, and Caluiniſts did to couer their ſchiſme withall, and yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:21656:37"/> long after, not with ſo much as any apparent cauſe, it yielded to the common ſchiſme of heretiks. The En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſhmen now, for the moſt part, doe prayſe and defend the diuiſion and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that is made: for that they ſtriue, for that they fly vnion, for that they caſt away Charity; they labour all they can, that agreement doe not ſucceede, and fraternall vnity be faſt knit in the bands of peace; and many of them ſay, that they would more willingly, and more eaſily haue vnion &amp; ſociety with the Turkes then with Papiſts? Is this to be ready to make concord? Is this the truth of their wordes, when they ſayd, that it was not their fault they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated not with the Church of Rome? Truly it cannot poſſibly be, that any vnion (which I thought might ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily haue beene atchieued) be made, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe they deteſt all hereſies, and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiks, and beleeue aright with the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Roman fayth, and be vnited vnto the ſame by perfect Charity.</p>
            <p n="27">27. Henry the 8. had in manner on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly contention with the Pope, and out of an hereticall ſpirit denyed his Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:21656:38"/> and toſſed with many diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed paſſions, tooke the ſame vnto himſelfe: in other thinges concerning fayth, forme of Religion, and Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall rites, he carryed himſelfe more moderatly. Vnder his Sonne Edward a child, and much more vnder Elizabeth, not only a ſeparation was made from the chiefe Biſhop Chriſt his vicar, and ſupreme Paſtor of the Chriſtian flocke, but alſo the vſe of Religion by mayne force, &amp; iniury was taken from Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes, and by publicke lawes (but made by Lay men) vtterly ſuppreſſed. Was there any lawfull Councell before for this matter? Were the obiections made againſt Catholikes diſcuſſed? Were the reaſons for their defence heard? Were they conuinced of any errour or impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in Religion? Was this iudgment made by any compete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Iudge? Nothing leſſe. Doth not the ſame violence, the ſame iniury, the ſame impiety ſtill remayne? How much doe they ſtriue in England, they eſpecially who ſeeme to haue care of their Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſuch as it is, leaſt the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine, ancie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, pious, &amp; preſcript worſhip of God be reſtored to Catholikes? Is
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:21656:38"/> this their meaning, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſay it is not? Their fault, that the ſchiſme is not taken away? They vrge reformation, but refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation be it neuer ſo iuſt, &amp; neceſſary, yet if it be made with ſchiſme, is a moſt fowle deformatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. That in deed is refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med that remaines the ſame in ſubſtance. Therefore Catholike Religion ought to haue remayned in England, and the ſubſtantiall practiſe of the ſame; if any thing had beene to be reformed, that <hi>ſeruatis ſeruandis</hi> might haue beene expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to reformation, but no other differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Religion (the former being ſuppreſſed or viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly kept vnder) was to be made, in ſo much as now there ſhould be two religions diſagreeing among themſelues and one contrary to the other: for if the latter be another Religion from the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, the former is not reformed, but, as much as lay in their power, is ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne, and a new ſet vp; but there cannot be two Religions of Chriſt, for there is but one only, and that with vs, I as haue ſhewed, as there is but one Church, one foundation, one Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="28">28. When as therefore amongſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther miſeryes I ſaw my ſelfe inuolued
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:21656:39"/> in inueterate ſchiſme, and all hope of v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion to be taken away, ſeeing Altar erected againſt Altar, &amp; deuided fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Charity of the Church, I neyther could nor ought, with ſafe conſcience to be preſent: wherfore remorſe of conſcience compelled me to returne, and it was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary that my <hi>Agar</hi> retourned to the moſt holy Roma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Church her miſtreſſe, hearing the voyce of the Angell check<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her, and ſaying: <note place="margin">Gen. 16.9.</note> 
               <hi>Reuertere ad Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minam tuam, &amp; humiliare ſub manu illius,</hi> returne to thy miſtreſſe, &amp; humble thy ſelfe vnder her hand or authority: that flight cold bring me nothing but ſhame and ruine: God commaunds me to be humbled vnder the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of my miſtreſſe, and in this I ought ſpecially to follow God. I would to God, that they to whome foliſhly I fled, would acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg their moſt miſerable ſpirituall eſtat, not only for hereſies, but alſo for their ſchiſme to be moſt deſperate: fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which ſchiſme now I haue ſhewed that they cannot be excuſed, becauſe they haue vnlawfully ſeparated themſelues from the true Church of Chriſt, which is our Catholike Roman Church. And this
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:21656:39"/> point affrighted me, becauſe ſchiſmatiks are excluded from being the Children of God: for <hi>Deum non habent patrem</hi> (ſaith <hi>S. Cyprian</hi>) <note place="margin">Lib. de ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitate Praelatoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </note> 
               <hi>qui Eccleſiam (veram) non ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent matrem:</hi> they haue not God for their Father, who haue not the (true) Church for their mother. Chriſt therfore died, <note place="margin">Ioan. 11.51.</note> 
               <hi>vt filios Dei qui diſperſi erant, congregaret in vnu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>;</hi> that he might gather in one, the children of God who were diſperſed: the death therfore of Chriſt did worke, and ſtill worketh, not only the redemption of men, but alſo the vnion of his Church. Before the death of Chriſt, the children of God were diſperſed, and deuided, ſome vnder the Law of Moyſes, others vnder the only Law of nature, being far aſunder one from the other, making to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether no one certayne, and vniuerſall Congregatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: but now the diuine wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome would ſo haue it, that al his faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full followers, &amp; true children by faith ſhould make ouer the whole world one ſociety, or fellowſhip, that they ſhold all make one warfare vnder their Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayn, and Emperour Chriſt, and vnder his banner, to wit, the holy and life-gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing Croſſe, vſing all the ſame milita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:21656:40"/> ſignes, and tokens of the Sacraments: and this ſociety, and congregation is a ſingular effect of the death of Chriſt, which procured, that diſagreeing Sects and innumerable courſes of life amongſt themſelues ſo different, and contrary, ſhould meete, and be combined in one Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnity, <note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.19</note> which truly is his worke <hi>qui fecit vtraque vnum,</hi> who made both one, and that by the Croſſe. Hereunto doth <hi>Anaſtaſius Synaita</hi> apply the wordes of God in the creation <hi>Congregentur aquae in locum vnum;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Anastaſ. 3. Hexam.</note> let the waters be gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red together in one place: This ſayth he belongeth to the Church, gathered to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether vnder the vnity of one fayth out of different people, countries, and ſects. And for this cauſe, Chriſt ſayd of his own Croſſe; <note place="margin">Ioan. 12.</note> 
               <hi>ſi exaltatus fuero à terra, om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia traham ad meipſum.</hi> If I ſhalbe exalted from the earth, I wil draw all vnto my ſelfe. <hi>S. Athanaſius</hi> ſayth, <note place="margin">Athanaſ. de Incarnat. verbi Dei.</note> 
               <hi>Exaltatus enim in cruce Dominus, vtroque extenſo brachio vtru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que populum ad ſe inuitauit, vt vtrumque am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexando in ſinum ſuum colligeret.</hi> Our Lord being exalted or lifted vpon the Croſſe, with both his armes ſtretched abroad inuited to himſelfe both people (Iew
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:21656:40"/> and Gentile) that by imbracing them both he might gather them together in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his boſome. There is therefore one boſome, betweene the armes of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour.</p>
            <p n="29">29. And in the ſame place <hi>S. Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſius</hi> thinkes it not to want myſtery, that Chriſt choſe the death of the Croſſe &amp; not Beheading, by which <hi>S. Iohn</hi> his precurſor died, nor cutting or deuiding of his body as <hi>Iſaias: Vt in morte</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>ſine mutilatione integrum corpus ſeruaret. &amp; cauſa ſubduceretur ijs qui Eccleſiam in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes cupiunt diſcindere,</hi> that in the death of Chriſt his entire body without maiming might be preſerued, and all pretext ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away from them who deſire to cut the Church aſunder into partes. And ſo hartily Chriſt eſteemed this vnity, as in that moſt feruent praier which he made in the laſt night of his life, <note place="margin">Ioan. 17.11 20.21.</note> he craued of his Father, that he would not ſuffer his diſciples, and other belieuers in him to depart from this vnity, <hi>vt credat mundus quia tu me miſisti,</hi> that the world may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue that thou haſt ſent me. But our Aduerſaryes little conſideringe theſe thinges will as much as is in them, haue
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:21656:41"/> the death, and Croſſe of Chriſt to be deſtitute of this moſt noble effect of v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and by their diuiſions &amp; ſchiſmes giue occaſion to Iewes and Infidells of rayling and blaſpheming of Chriſt, and ſaying that he was not the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne of God, or ſent by him, ſeeing the ſociety or Church founded by him, doth not ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt, but is euer now and then to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued, or deuided into partes; the Church of Chriſt is one houſe, and one family; he who drawes himſelfe from this family, that goeth forth out of this houſe, he belongs not to the family of Chriſt, he is depriued of ſaluation, as who were not in the Arke, <note place="margin">Gen. 3.</note> were loſt, and periſhed in the floud. The Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants haue cut themſelues from the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Chriſt, which is the only Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Roman Church, and thoſe who are inſeparably vnited with the ſame: therfore they are not members of Chriſt and therefore Chriſt is not their head, neyther doth he infuſe his holy Spirit, and gifts into them: they are therefore rotten members, and already cut of, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they haue cut themſelues off wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedly of their own accord from the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy:
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:21656:41"/> 
               <hi>Sunt palmites</hi> (ſayth S. Auguſtine) <note place="margin">Auguſt. Epiſt. 50.</note> 
               <hi>à vite praeciſi, nulli vſui niſi igni apti: neque poteſt eſſe particeps diuinae Caritatis, qui eſt hoſtis vnitatis:</hi> they are branches cut off from the vyne, fit for no other vſe then the fire: <note place="margin">Ezech. 15.3</note> neyther can he be partaker of Gods charity, who is an enemy of vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. So he.</p>
            <p n="30">30. Of all ſpirituall help (if they think themſelues to haue any) they haue made ſhipwrack by their ſchiſme. <hi>Si lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guis hominum loquar &amp; Angelorum,</hi> (ſayth S. Paul) <note place="margin">1. Cor. 13.1.</note> 
               <hi>Caritatem autem non habeam, nihil ſum, nihil mihi prodest.</hi> If I ſhall ſpeake with the tongues of men, and Angels, and haue not Charity, I am nothinge, it auayles me nothing. Out of which wordes of the Apoſtle <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently admoniſheth, <note place="margin">Auguſt. de Baptiſmo Lib. 1. c. 9.</note> no good worke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny way to auayle a Schiſmatike. The ſame, and more then once, hath <hi>S. Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pryan</hi> deliuered. <note place="margin">Cypria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. lib. 4. Epiſt. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Etſi occiſus propter nomen Christi poſtmodum fuerit extra Eccleſiam con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutus, &amp; ab vnitate atque caritate diuiſus, coronari in morte non poterit:</hi> although one after that he is out of the Church, and is deuided from the vnity, and charity of the ſame, be killed for the name of
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:21656:42"/> Chriſt, he cannot be crowned in his death. The ſame he vrgeth in other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as <hi>Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 1. <hi>&amp; ad Iulianum, &amp; tract. de ſimp. Praelatorum, ſeu de vnitate Eccleſiae: &amp; de Oratione Dominica,</hi> whome <hi>S. Chryſostome</hi> followes <hi>in Epiſt. ad Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſios. Hom.</hi> 11.</p>
            <p n="31">31. Let the Proteſtants, I beſeech them, conſider what an enormous ſinne they haue committed by this curſed ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration, becauſe that ſchiſme deſtroyes the Church, for it is the ſaying of Chriſt, <note place="margin">Luc. 11.17.</note> 
               <hi>Omne Regnum in ſe diuiſum deſolabitur,</hi> eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry kingdome deuided in it ſelfe ſhalbe brought to deſolation: and of <hi>S. Paul,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Galat. 5.15.</note> 
               <hi>Videte ne dum inuicem mordetis, inuicem con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummamini.</hi> Take head leaſt whiles you bite one another, yee be not conſumed one of another: and this cryme of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying the Church may be ſayd to be that ſinne agaynſt the holy Ghoſt, that Chriſt auouched not to be forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen in this world, nor in the next, <note place="margin">Math. 12.31.</note> as <hi>S. Ambroſe</hi> ſheweth. <note place="margin">Ambroſ. 2. de Paenit. cap. 4.</note> So that moſt wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked harlot in the booke of Kings, had rather that there ſhould be no child, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that it ſhould be brought vp in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome of the true mother, and exclaymed
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:21656:42"/> againſt her, ſaying, <note place="margin">3. Reg. 3.26.</note> 
               <hi>nec mihi nec tibi, ſed di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidatur;</hi> let the child neither be giuen to me nor thee, but let it be deuided: the Schiſmaticks labour al they can that the true and entier Fayth be not kept in the boſome of the true mother the Church: they goe about to dead it, that it may neither be kept aliue with them nor vs: but they preuayle nothing; and let thoſe know that to be ſpoken of them, <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſt 10.8.</note> 
               <hi>qui diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſipat ſepem, mordebit eum coluber,</hi> the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent ſhall byte him that breateth down the hedge.</p>
            <p n="32">32. And it is no meruayle that the Engliſhmen haue fallen into many He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies, &amp; that Puritaniſme doth ſway ſo much, albeyt when firſt they made their ſchiſme they were neither infected with the Lutherane or Calumia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hereſies. For as <hi>Irenaeus</hi> doth notably teach vs, <note place="margin">Iren. lib. 3. cap. 40. &amp; lib. 4. cap. 43.</note> thoſe who are cut of from the Church, do not drinke out of the fountayne of the ſpirit of God, but do digg for themſelues by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lakes, and do fall into moſt groſſe er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours agaynſt the truth of Fayth. In like manner S. <hi>Cyprian</hi> makes the Catholike Church the roote, the fountayne, the ſunne; <note place="margin">Cypria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. lib. de ſimplic. Praelat.</note> that as a branch hath his life fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:21656:43"/> the roote, the riuer his water from the fountayne, the ſunne-beame his light &amp; ſpendour from the ſunne: ſo the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity of true beleefe to be had by our v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with the Catholike Church: they therfore who haue cut themſelues from it, cannot haue the truth of fayth, but muſt neceſſarily fall into errours; for they are trees without a roote, ryuers without a fountayne, &amp; ſunne-beames without a ſunne; hereof it comes that the Fathers out of theſe, and the like rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons doe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uince, that ſchiſme in the end breaks forth into hereſy: for he who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſeth to haue vnity with the Catholike Church, will alſo refuſe to learne of her the truth of Fayth, of which ſhe alone is the treaſurer, &amp; preſeruer. <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> very well defines this matter, when he ſayth: <note place="margin">Augu. lib. 2. contra Creſcon c. 7.</note> 
               <hi>Inueteratum Schiſma eſſe ipſammet haereſim,</hi> inueterate ſchiſme to be hereſy it ſelfe. And <hi>S. Cyprian</hi> worthily findeth in euery ſchiſme that hereſy at leaſt, wherby is taken away one or two arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of our Creed; <hi>Credo Sanctam Eccleſiam Catholicam, &amp; Remiſsionem peccatorum:</hi> I belieue the holy Catholike Church, &amp; the Remiſſion or forgiuenes of ſinnes:
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:21656:43"/> for they who beleeue the holy Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Church to be the true Church of Chriſt, they cannot if they thus be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue depart from her; and in caſe they depart, then truly they do not belieue the Catholike Church to be the true Church of Chriſt. So Saint <hi>Augustine</hi> ſayth of the Donatiſts, <note place="margin">Aug. hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſ. 69. ad Quod vult Deum.</note> that they had turned their ſchiſme into hereſy. And <hi>S. Ambroſe</hi> in the funeral Oration had of his brother approuing his fact for that he had fled from the <hi>Luciferian</hi> Church, as I now from the Churches of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, ſayth: <hi>Non putauit Fidem eſſe in ſchiſmate: nam etſi Fidem in Deum tenerent, tamen erga Dei Eccleſiam non tenerent, cuius patiebantur velut quoſdam artus diuidi &amp; me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bra lacerari, Etenim cùm propter Eccleſiam Chriſtus paſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> ſit, &amp; Chriſti corpus Eccleſia ſit, non videtur ab ijs exhiberi Christo fides, à quibus euacua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur eius paſsio, corpuſque distrahitur.</hi> He thought not that there was any fayth in ſchiſme: for although they kept their fayht towards God, yet they kept it not towards the Church of God, of which they permitted certayne ioyntes to be deuided, and members to be torne: tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly whereas Chriſt ſuffered his paſſion
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:21656:44"/> for the Church, and the Church is the body of Chriſt, they ſeeme not to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue in Chriſt, by whome his Paſſion is made voyd, &amp; his body diſmembred.</p>
            <p n="33">33. Was I then with ſo great do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of my ſoule to remayne amongſt Heretikes, and Schimatickes? God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid. I am troubled with bitter griefe of mynd, that I remayned ſo long a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, that I tooke wicked ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, and fought agaynſt my Mother, agaynſt the Catholike truth, and that I wrote bookes of the Eccleſiaſtical Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Wealth ſtuffed with hereſyes, which I vtterly abhorre, and deteſt, &amp; that I haue warred in the infamous tents of heretiks, not without the perpetuall blot, or infamy of my Name. I now loath, and am aſhamed of my ſo great offence, and craue humbly, and with al ſubmiſſion, pardon for this wickednes of God, moſt good, moſt great, of my Sauiour Chriſt, and of his ſupreme Vicar, or Subſtitute on Earth the Biſhop of Rome: and ſubmit all my faultes to the ſingular Clemency of the ſame chiefe Paſtour, becauſe that he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be iudged of none, ſits as ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:21656:44"/> Iudge of al, moſt fully ſuſteining the perſon of Chriſt in the militant Church: and I confidently hope that as our Lord doth willingly open to his Penitent the boſome of his mercy; ſo I ſhalbe imbraced in the armes of Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency by his Holynes. The exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of <hi>S. Cyprian</hi> againſt Pope <hi>Stephen</hi> the firſt, very much reprehended, and condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned alſo by the Catholike Church, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed me a while in my naughtynes of reſiſting the Pope; but now my filthy fall hath with myne owne dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger taught me how eaſily Biſhops fall from the right path of Fayth, who lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the <hi>Cynoſura,</hi> or Pole-ſtarre, that is, the moſt certayne, and ſecure direction of the Biſhop of Rome, follow, to their deſtruction, their own fooliſh fancyes. I would to God, that as <hi>S. Cyprian</hi> with the ſhedding of his own bloud, did blot out all the ſpot of his former animoſity: ſo alſo, that there may be graunted vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, who for the multitude, &amp; great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of my faultes, haue incomparably exceeded his fall, opportunity, &amp; grace to blot out alſo with my bloud, thoſe ſoule ſpots, and by that meanes to te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtify
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:21656:45"/> the Catholike truth; which, when my inke ſhould fayle me, I am moſt ready by the help of God, to his prayſe and honour, for the aduauncement of the holy Catholike Church, and glory of the Sea Apoſtolike, to ſeale with my bloud. <hi>Adſit Deus.</hi> God ſecond and aſſiſt me. <hi>Rome,</hi> the 24. of <hi>Nouember</hi> 1622. ſtylo nouo.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:21656:45"/>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:21656:46"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:21656:46"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:21656:47"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:21656:47"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:21656:48"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:21656:48"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:21656:49"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:21656:49"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:21656:50"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:21656:50"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:21656:51"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:21656:51"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:21656:52"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:21656:52"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:21656:53"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:21656:53"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
